We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Did you know that as we
age our telomeres shorten?
Telomeres are a series
of DNA sequences
that protect the ends of our chromosomes
from becoming frayed or tangled.
As it turns out, a plant
based diet and lifestyle
can effectively reverse cellular
aging by elongating telomeres.
Here’s the story.
Identifying simple strategies
to prevent or delay age-related
diseases is a major
public health concern.
But how could you measure
the effects of such strategies?
Well, telomere length is a reliable
hallmark of biological aging
and the risk of developing
age-related chronic diseases.
What is a telomere,
and why does it matter
how long they are?
Telomere comes from the Greek for
"end" "part" of our chromosomes.
Telomeres cap the ends
of our chromosomes
like shoelace tips to essentially
keep our DNA from fraying.
Telomere length is important since
there's a minimum length required,
but every time our cells divide,
a bit of the telomere is lost
and once they get too short,
the cell can die.
That's why telomeres are sometimes
called the molecular clock of cells.
Every year they get shorter and
shorter, kind of like life's fuse,
but in some people that fuse
burns faster than in others.
Accelerated telomere shortening
has been identified as a key biomarker
for accelerated aging, disease risk,
and diminished longevity.
But there's some good news.
Telomere shortening can be
counteracted by an enzyme
in our cells called telomerase.
Telomerase can replenish the lost
bits and elongate our telomeres.
So how can we boost this enzyme
to, in effect, reverse cellular aging?
Exercise may help.
Those with high levels
of physical activity
have longer telomeres,
whereas obese individuals and smokers
tend to have shorter telomeres,
along with those getting
inadequate sleep.
But what about nutrition?
Globally, we might expect that any
antioxidant or anti-inflammatory diet
could be protective for telomeres.
So we're talking like
a whole food plant-based diet
with a reduced intake of meat and,
in fact, swapping out animal protein
in general in favor
of plant-based proteins.
Given that plant-based foods
have well-known antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory effects,
there are fair grounds to believe
that the consumption
of plant-based foods
can help to counteract
telomere attrition,
but you don't know if it actually
would, until you put it to the test.
Dr. Dean Ornish, along
with the Nobel laureate
who co-discovered
the telomerase enzyme,
studied the effects of
comprehensive lifestyle changes
on telomerase activity
and telomere length
using the same plant-based
diet and lifestyle program
shown to reverse the progression
of heart disease and
early-stage prostate cancer, and
maybe even early-stage Alzheimer's.
And telomere length shortened
in the control group,
and they aged five years
as expected,
but didn't just not shorten
as much or hold steady,
but actually lengthened in
the plant-based lifestyle group.
Whereas in a similar study
across a similar time frame,
there was no difference in
telomere length when just giving
people the more typical low-fat dairy,
skinless chicken breast,
generic-type
healthier dietary advice.
Antioxidant-rich plant foods
help maintain telomere length.
In contrast, total and saturated fat
intake and consumption
of refined flour grains,
meat and meat products,
and soda relate
to shorter telomeres.
People eating more
anti-inflammatory diets
tend to have longer telomeres,
and the greater the anti-inflammatory
potential of the diet over time,
the greater potential
to significantly slow down
the rate of telomere shortening.
Those with the most
pro-inflammatory diets
had almost twice the risk of
accelerated telomere shortening.
The most pro-inflammatory
food component is saturated fat,
found in meat, dairy, eggs and junk,
along with other pro-inflammatory
food components like
cholesterol and trans fat.
Omega-3's tend to be
anti-inflammatory,
but when put to the test,
fish oil supplements
failed to have any
significant telomere effects.
The most anti-inflammatory
food component is fiber.
And indeed, if you look at dietary
fiber intake and telomere length
in a representative sampling
of thousands of US adults,
even though nobody
was eating enough,
the more fiber people consumed,
the longer their telomeres
tended to be.
Since there appeared
to be a straight-line increase,
they could do the math,
and it appeared that just a 10-gram
increase in fiber per 1000 calories
would equate to four fewer years
of biologic aging,
whereas, for example,
the consumption of soda
appeared to increase cell aging
by almost two years
per daily serving.
Now, of course, diets high in fiber
and diets with significant amounts
of fruits, vegetables, and
whole grains go hand in hand.
So fiber may just be a marker
for eating lots of whole
healthy plant foods,
but are there any specific plants
associated with telomere lengthening?
We'll find out next.
Telomere length is considered
a biomarker of aging:
shorter telomeres are associated
with decreased life expectancy
and increased rates of
age-related chronic diseases.
Telomere shortening has been
shown to be accelerated
by oxidative stress and inflammation.
So since plant foods contain
plenty of compounds
with antioxidant and
anti-inflammatory properties,
it's plausible that their
sustained consumption
might help counteract
telomere attrition.
And indeed, if you pull all the best
studies on the impact of nutrition
on telomere length, the consumption
of vegetables, fruits, beans and nuts
has been associated with positive
effects on markers of inflammation
and oxidative stress
in parallel with longer telomeres.
By contrast, processed meats,
alcoholic and sugar sweetened beverages,
and other foods rich in
saturated fats, alcohol, and sugar
are linked to an increase
in inflammation
and oxidative stress
in parallel with shorter telomeres.
In my last video on telomeres,
I featured a randomized controlled trial
showing a whole food,
plant-based diet and lifestyle program
could actually lengthen telomeres.
Is it just because they cut out the junk?
Those eating the most ultra-processed
foods have been found
to have almost twice the odds
of having short telomeres.
Maybe it's because they cut out
the processed meat,
like bacon, ham, hot dogs,
lunchmeat, sausage,
which has been associated with
not only cancer and diabetes risk
but shorter telomeres as well,
meaning accelerated cellular aging,
though just having
something like a steak
was not similarly associated
with telomere length.
Processed meat, but not
unprocessed red meat,
is associated with
shorter telomere length.
This is perhaps due to the particularly
high concentrations of glycotoxins,
the advanced glycation end products,
as well as carcinogenic nitrosamines
in the processed meat that may promote
inflammation and oxidative stress.
The only unprocessed meat associated
with shorter telomeres was poultry.
For dairy, it appears to be the milk fat.
A national survey of
thousands of Americans
found an association between
increased biological aging and
the consumption of high-fat milk.
Even with people just
going up like 1% milk fat
(from like 1% milk to 2% milk,
low-fat milk to reduced fat milk)
appeared to have more than 4 years
of additional biological aging.
We think it's because of the saturated
fat, given that saturated fats trigger
an inflammatory response. Not all
plant foods are good for you, though.
French fries and potato chip
consumption is associated
with shorter telomeres.
Yes, fiber intake goes hand-in-hand
with longer telomeres,
as does higher vegetable
and fruit consumption,
but that may be trumped
by a deep fryer.
What about the consumption of a
high fat whole plant food like nuts?
We know higher telomere-building
enzyme activity is associated
with a higher dietary
antioxidant score,
and botanically, seeds are
packed with antioxidants
and by seeds, they mean any food
you can put in the ground
and sprout a whole plant, like whole
grains, beans, chickpeas, lentils, nuts.
They're naturally enriched
in antioxidant compounds
that protect the seed
DNA from damage.
Four weeks of Navy beans
didn't seem to affect
telomere length, though.
What about nuts?
Well, based on how much your
telomeres shorten every year,
you can estimate the rate of aging.
In other words, two people can have
the same chronological age,
same calendar age, but suffer
more or less effective cellular aging.
So, for example, if you smoke
a pack a day for a decade,
your cells may age
about 3 years faster.
Or, if you drink soda every day,
it's like almost 2 years
of additional aging.
So what about nuts?
U.S. adults of the same age would
experience almost 2 years less
biologic aging per ounce of nuts
and seeds consumed per day,
the amount I recommend
in my free Daily Dozen app.
The estimated biologic aging
advantage would be nearly 1 year
for each 100 calories of nuts
and seeds consumed every day.
The researchers conclude that, clearly,
consumption of nuts and seeds
accounts for meaningfully
lower levels of biologic aging
in U.S. men and women.
But that's just an association.
You don't know if nuts can slow telomere
shortening until you put it to the test.
A randomized controlled trial
investigating whether the inclusion
of one or two ounces
of walnuts a day
for two years would help
maintain telomere length,
which normally shortens with age.
In the control group, their
telomeres shortened as expected
over those two years, whereas the
walnut group telomeres maintained
their length, though the difference
didn't reach statistical significance.
Now, that was measuring
average telomere length,
and it's probably more telling
to look at how long
the shortest telomeres are
rather than the average,
and if you do that, look at
the percentage of telomeres
that are particularly short,
the walnut group does edge
out over the control group.
It's well established that the length
of the shortest telomeres is
the key biomarker
of the onset of senescence.
The researchers conclude
that the inclusion of walnuts
in the regular diet for
2 years tends to delay
leukocyte telomere shortening
in older individuals.
A study on pistachio consumption,
2 ounces a day for 4 months,
reduced signs of DNA damage,
but did not significantly slow
the rate of telomere shortening.
And this study, which randomized
people to eat more mixed nuts,
found a higher risk of telomere
shortening in the nut group,
for which the researchers
could offer no explanation.
So it's not clear whether nuts
help with telomeres or not.
Most supplement intervention
studies observed null effects
on telomere length as well,
with the exception of green tea.
Thirty-six elderly women were
randomly divided into two groups:
exercise alone or exercise with
green tea consumption for 5 months,
and a significant boost in telomere
length in the green tea group
with no change from the placebo.
Green tea is essentially a green leafy
vegetable we dip in hot water.
How about eating green leafy vegetables,
in fact the healthiest kind:
cruciferous vegetables like broccoli,
cabbage, collards and kale.
They pitted raw versus cooked and
found that cooked was better than raw
for reducing DNA damage
from a carcinogen,
but raw was more anti-inflammatory.
Consequently, to fully exploit
the complexity of the
health-promoting potential
of Ethiopian kale, and by extension
maybe other cruciferous,
a mix of both raw and cooked
vegetables should be part of the diet.
OK, but what about
for boosting
the telomere-lengthening
age-reversal enzyme?
Raw or cooked.
Which do you think?
A short-term dietary intervention
showed that cooked but not raw
boosted telomerase activity
in as short as five days,
eating one and a quarter cups
of this kale a day.
It was thought that you'd
need like 4 months of a change
to affect telomeres,
but this study provides,
for the first time, evidence
that telomerase activity
can respond in a matter of days
to a food intervention,
but not just any food,
but the healthiest food out there:
cruciferous dark green
leafy vegetables.
Finally today,
Dr. Dean Ornish showed
that his plant-based diet,
exercise, and stress
management intervention
could in effect reverse
the aging of our DNA.
What effect might the stress
management component have had?
In my Research Into Reversing Aging video,
I highlighted Dean Ornish's landmark study
showing that a low-fat,
whole foods, plant-based diet
high in fruits, vegetables, whole grains, beans,
along with walking, stress
management, and support
could not only reverse heart, open up
arteries without drugs and surgery,
and potentially reverse the progression
of early-stage prostate cancer,
but was the first intervention EVER
shown to increase telomerase activity,
the enzyme that builds and maintains these caps
at the tips of our chromosomes called telomeres,
which appear to slow the
aging of our cells.
Yes, this new finding was exciting
and should encourage people
to adopt a healthy lifestyle in order to avoid
or combat cancer and age-related diseases,
but was it the diet, the exercise,
or the stress management?
That's what researchers have
been trying to tease out
in the six years since
this study was published.
Let's look at stress first.
In the film "The Holiday",
Cameron Diaz exclaimed,
“Severe stress ... causes the DNA in our cells to
shrink until they can no longer replicate.”
Did Hollywood get
the science right?
Do people who are stressed
have shorter telomeres?
To answer that question, researchers
measured the telomere lengths
in mothers of
chronically ill children—
what could be more
stressful than that?
The longer a woman had spent being
the main carer of her ill child,
the shorter were
her telomeres.
The extra telomere shortening
in these stressed mothers
was equivalent to that caused
by at least a decade of aging.
We see the same thing in
caregivers of Alzheimer's patients,
and those suffering severe
work related exhaustion.
Even those abused as children,
may grow up with shorter telomeres.
Not much we can do
about our past,
but if we manage our stress can we
grow some of our telomeres back?
Well, if you go off to a meditation
retreat and meditate for 500 hours
you can indeed boost your
telomerase activity.
600 hours of meditation may
be beneficial as well,
but come on, there's got
to be a quicker fix...
and this exciting
new study delivered!
Caregivers of family
members with dementia
randomized to just 12 minutes of
daily meditation for 8 weeks,
so just about 10 hours in total,
experienced significant benefit.
Better mental and psychological function
accompanied by an increase in telomerase activity,
suggesting improvement in
stress-induced cellular aging.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.